I'm going to share a little Neuroscience
tidbit love but I think it's one that
you'll appreciate um most people don't
know this but there's a brain structure
called the anterior mid singulate cortex
as we pointed out before that's a noun
it's a name it doesn't mean anything we
could call it the the Cookie Monster
right but what's interesting about this
brain area is there now a lot of data in
humans that's some mouse study showing
that when people do something they don't
want to do like add three hours of
exercise per day or per week or when
people who are trying to diet and lose
weight resist eating something right
when people do anything that they and
this is the important part that they
don't want to do right it's not about
adding more work it's about adding more
work that you don't want to do yes this
brain area gets bigger yep now here's
what's especially interesting about this
brain area to me and by the way I'm only
learning this recently because it's new
data but there's a lot of it the
anterior mid singulate
cortex is smaller in obese
people it gets bigger when they diet MH
it's larger in athletes MH it's
especially large or grows larger in
people that see themselves as challenged
and overcome some challenge
right and in people that live a very
long
time this area keeps its size in many
ways scientists are starting to think of
the anterior mid singulate cortex not
just as one of the seats of willpower
right but perhaps actually the seat of
the will to live see now we're talking
and when I learned about the anterior
mid singulate cortex I was like almost
out of my seat and I've been in the
Neuroscience game since I was 20 we the
same age and I was so pumped because
I've heard of the amydala fear
prefrontal cortex it's planning and
action I could tell you every brain area
and every I teach neuro Anatomy to
medical students but when I started
seeing the data on the anter mid
singulate cortex I was like whoa this is
interesting yep and all the data point
to the fact that we can build this area
up yep but that as quickly as we build
it up if we don't continue to invest in
things that are hard for us that we
don't want to do that's the part that
feels so gogin esque sir to me that we
don't want to do like if you love The
ice bath yeah I love the ice bath you go
from 1 minute to 10 minutes guess what
your anterior mid singulate cortex did
not grow none but if you hate the cold
water if you're afraid of drowning and
you get into water and put your head
under
yep then you're anterior mid and survive
then the anterior mid singulate cortex
gets bigger but if you don't do it the
next day or if you do it the next day
and you enjoy it because hey hey I did
it yesterday woohoo happy me Merry
Christmas as you say Merry Christmas
guess what the anterior mid singulate
cortex shrinks again yep to me this is
one of the most important discoveries
that Neuroscience has ever made MH
because it's that I don't want to do
something but do it anyway that's right
that grows this area and it's almost
like I have a friend he's been sober 30
years from alcohol and he always says
you know the amazing thing about
addiction is there's a cure the problem
is it only works one day at a time yep
and so you have to renew it every day
that's right so the Anor mid singulate
text to me when I learned about it two
two things went off in my head whoa this
is super interesting and two I got to
tell David gogins about this and I
waited until now to tell you because I
felt like I well for obvious reasons I
wanted to tell you and I wanted to tell
you here well I love that because that's
how I've lived my entire life I don't
know anything about that but people go
man you have such a strong
will it's something that you build like
I never forgot I was on a podcast one
time and this dude goes you were blessed
with a strong
mind
like the hell you talking about it's
blessed with a strong mind you that's
something that you have to
develop you develop that over years
decades of suffering and going back into
the suffer that's why a lot of people
who graduate Navy SEAL training they
were no like in my I talk about very
open all the
time a lot of guys don't go don't want
to go back into that water they want to
go back into the hard stuff it maybe not
in anything hard anything hard in life
once you get through it it's like you
become a
p like how many PS you know want to go
back to p camp
none when something sucks so bad in life
this is on this that we're talking about
now very few people want to go back
they're happy they grad
graduated I realized I'm the same way I
don't want to go
back I have to go back I must go back
because that is exactly where all the
knowledge of my life exist was back
there and what you're exactly you're
talking about well I didn't know
anything about this but how I grew a
will was constantly doing these things
to now it's just life
I wake up while it still sucks it's just
life you don't sit back and like oh my
God like I have days I don't want to do
but I know I'm going to do
it I know from years of just doing it so
that that that's that's beautiful and
this is why I came on here with you
today and I'm I'm glad you're talking
about this because human beings need to
hear this they need to stop hearing
these
hacks on this and that there's no
[__] hack bro there's no [__] hack
yeah you may this and that and saunas
and all this [__] that they yeah it's
great there is no [__] life hack to
grow that thing how do you grow it do it
and do it and do it and do it that's the
hack the hack is gonna [__] suck and
that's what I realized that's what I
realized life that's why I want to come
on here today I didn't want to come on
here and talk about no [__] passion
and purpose and how to get the [__] out
of bed and how to hit a [__] alarm
clock and all this catchphrase
[__] cuz that wasn't how I
lived I was how I lived I lived I woke
up like every human being does and goes
[__] man I'm a [__] piece of [__]
today how the hell is this gonna work
out for me and you fight that and you
fight that you don't override it it's no
override button it's the conversation in
your [__] in your head so how do you
do that we don't have enough these
conversations about about the real
conversation that every human being is
having and they have no idea how to get
out of it but they
do it's that [__] right there man you
gotta build your will how do you build
your will exactly what you said man
exactly what you said well I feel like
knowing the name of something anterior
mid singulate cortex doesn't
fundamentally change us but one thing I
like about biology is that willpower if
somebody feels they don't have it feels
like this thing that other people have
but everybody unless they're brain
damaged like a hole right through their
head has two anter mid singulate cortex
one on each side of their brain everyone
has one they have two so I feel like
it's just a question of opening the
portal and the portal what I again I'm s
to say 10 times and forgive me is I
think people go oh I do hard things I do
sets to failure and then I do four
straps I love training with weights I
love doing sets to failure I even like
for stps but guess what I like for stps
so I can I'll tell you they don't build
my anterior mid singulate cortex right
because I like to do it that's right
anything you like to do is not going to
enhance this aspect of willpower and it
seems so obvious once you hear it you
kind of go oh yeah of course but I
think you really close that Loop for
people when you share what you're
sharing today and what you've shared
elsewhere before as well when you're
trying to explain the friction is the
critical ingredient right and I think
people think oh if it's effort well then
I'm getting better that's part of it
necessary but not sufficient as we say
in science but the suck
part The Haunt being haunted the stick
they're really unpleasant terms very
these are probably the most unpleasant
terms we've ever used on this podcast
very those are the those are the levers
those are the gears and without those
this thing that you're talking about
David goggin mhm as a verb right you
know I sometimes make the joke but it's
not a joke right goggin is a name MH and
it's a verb people go I'm GNA goggin
that right right but that's I think
again I'm not a psychologist but I think
that's what you're talking about the
stick the friction being haunted it's
the suck part that grows this anterior
mid singulate cortex so now you know why
there's so many people that fail in this
world to figure out
their
purpose their purpose in life where do I
go because to grow
that while you may not look like me how
my daily life
looks it don't look
fun don't look
fun so it's a choice that people have to
make in life but what's so funny about
it is even the richest of Rich who have
everything they always ask me this
question
I feel like I'm missing
something I don't feel like I'm missing
[__] I don't have what you all have but
you'll never in my life hear me tell you
I'm missing something everybody is
they're missing this
feeling I found it long time ago I found
it right there in that willpower thing
when you're nothing nothing and CH
yourself into something like
me you call it happiness peace whatever
the [__] you want to call
it people are missing exactly what went
on with David Goggins why don't you
smile I do I do but I figure something
out that's why I am never you'll never
hear me say I'm missing something I
found it years ago you find it in the
suck you find it in the suck and you
find it repeatedly in the suck to the
point where you know exactly who you are
most people are missing something
because they don't know who they
are they never examined themselves they
they've never done this experiment on
themselves the labat we're all Lab Rats
but you're also the
scientist you create your own self most
people are missing something because
there's so much trapped in there I want
I want to say potential I think that's
word used out too much too there's so
much in you that God or wherever the
hell you believe in or if you're atheist
in you that you have not un unlocked
that you walk around with this gorgeous
wife or or great husband all this money
like God I feel like I'm missing
something yeah because it's about 75% of
you is still [__] in there still
chained up because you just didn't want
to find your willpower didn't want to
find your soul your will your heart your
determination your guts your courage and
what that looks like it looks scary like
your little scary lab I went in scary to
wake up every day and say I'm stupid but
I want to figure out a way to be
smarter versus saying man I just can't
do that so you limit this box so your
box becomes so small of things you can
do my box wasn't even a box it was a
[__] little like little pinhole and
then through examining myself getting
some willpower some courage it became
bigger than this table but that's what
we all do that's why I want to come here
today and talk to you about real [__]
not no [__] like hacks there's no
hacks bro it's you against you you
against you and if you misunderstand
that you have a real problem real
problem I can understand you
misunderstand me running down the street
shirt off [__] this no yeah I can I can
get it I get it if you misunderstand
what I'm saying right now today the
problem is you and you don't want to fix
[Music]
it